Guide to the Council of Higher Education Ministries Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Council of Higher Education Ministries records
1988-2007
RG 226
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.0
(2 boxes)
The archives include minutes and financial information for the Council for Higher Education Ministries' work groups: the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, Higher Education Ministries Arena, and United Ministries in Higher Education.
Council of Higher Education Ministries
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Council for Higher Education Ministries, 2007
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Council for Higher Education Ministries (CHEM) was established in the mid 1990s as an umbrella agency with three work groups: the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry (CESCM), Higher Education Ministries Arena (HEMA), and United Ministries in Higher Education (UMHE). CHEM dissolved as a 501 c 3 not-for-profit corporation in 2007 and its activities merged into the National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA.
The three CHEM work groups were all involved with ecumenical work with students and had overlapping goals and participants. The Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry was founded in 1987, shortly after the collapse of the earlier National Ecumenical Student Christian Council. CESCM was established "in order to create new opportunities for involving students and campus ministries in the work to rebuild an ecumenical student Christian ministry in the United States." In 1995 the CESCM was affiliated with the World Student Christian Federation as a member movement.
In the late 1980s, negotiators from United Ministries in Education and the Education in the Society Unit of the National Council of churches began exploring the possibility of creating a new national higher educationon ministries entity to be lodged within the reorganized NCC. The result was the creation of the Higher Education Ministries Arena (HEMA), first as a part of Ecumenical Ministries in Education (a program ministry of the Education, Communications, and Discipleship Unit of the NCC) and later separately incorporated. According to a 1992 memo, the Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Education (previously and later known as United Ministries in Higher Education) continued to exist after the formation of HEMA because "certain partnerships to be maintained and services to be rendered....could not be adequately sustained through the Higher Education Ministries Arena."
United Ministries in Higher Education (UMHE) was comprised of the higher education staff of the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Presbyterian Church USA, United Church of Christ, Church of the Brethren, and Moravian Church. It characterized itself as "a national staff collective to provide vision and oversight for developing progressive, ecumenical student Christian leadership." The last records from UMHE date from 2005.
Higher Education Ministries Arena evolved into The Ecumenical Campus Ministries Team (ECMT), which is part of the Education and Leadership Ministries Commission of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA. ECMT provides a structure through which seven denominations work ecumenically to achieve common goals in higher education ministries: American Baptist Churches, USA, the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Episcopal Church, Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, Presbyterian Church (USA), United Church of Christ, and United Methodist Church.
Scope and Contents
The archives include minutes and financial information for the Council for Higher Education Ministries' work groups: the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, Higher Education Ministries Arena, and United Ministries in Higher Education. The final series provides documentation of the Celebrate national ecumenical christian student gatherings held 1997 - 2005. These materials documenting ecumenical student Christian work complement other various collections at the Yale Divinity School Library, including the archives of the Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry in Record Group No. 107 and United Ministries in Higher Education archives in Record Group No. 104.
Arrangement
I. Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, 1988-2007
II. Higher Education Ministries Arena, 1991-2007
III. United Ministries in Higher Education, 1988-2005
IV. Celebrate Ecumenical Student Conferences, 1997-2007
Universities and colleges -- Religion; Church work with students; College students -- Religious life; Council of Higher Education Ministries; Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry; United Ministries in Higher Education; Higher Education Ministries Arena
- Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, 1988-2007; Series I
  - "Partners Meeting" minutes, 1988-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - CESCM Spring and Fall meeting minutes, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Steering Committee minutes, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Committee minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial reports, 1993-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Higher Education Ministries Arena, 1991-2007; Series II
  - Minutes, 1991-2006 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Financial reports, 1993-2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- United Ministries in Higher Education, 1988-2005; Series III
  Scope and Contents
  In 1979 UMHE changed its name to United Ministries in Education, joining with Ministries in Public Education. In 1988 this partnership was ended and the UMHE was reorganized as The Higher Education Ministries Team of United Ministries in Higher Education (though still incorporated as United Ministries in Education).
  - United Ministries in Education (UME) Annual and Corporate meeting minutes; staff meeting minutes; "Basic Policies" document, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13a)
  - Higher Education Ministries Team, United Ministries in Higher Education (HEMT/UMHE)meeting minutes; report of Administrative Coordinator, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - HEMT/UMHE Policy Committee meeting minutes; Report: "Evaluation, 1989-1992 and Recommendations, 1993-1995" (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - UMHE Staff meeting minutes; Board of Directors and Policy Committee meeting minutes; list of resources created by UMHE, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - UMHE Staff meeting minutes; "Plan of Ministry 1995", Board of Directors and Policy Committee meeting minutes, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - UMHE "Proposals for the Future"; Policy Committee meeting minutes, incl. re. working under Council for Higher Education Ministries; Staff meeting minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - UMHE meeting minutes, incl. re. scheduled disbanding of UMHE by end of 1999, rationale for continuing its existence, 1998-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - CHEM-UMHE meeting minutes, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Financial reports, 1995-2005 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Celebrate Ecumenical Student Conferences, 1997-2007; Series IV
  - Celebrate III (Ridgecrest Conference Center, Asheville, NC 1998 Dec 30-1999 Jan 3), Planning Team meeting minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Celebrate III, flyer, brochure, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Celebrate III, financial reports, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Celebrate IV (Albuquerque Convention 2002 Dec- 2003 Jan), financial reports, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Celebrate V (New Orleans, 2006 Dec.28-2007 Jan 1), Design Team meeting minutes, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Celebrate V, financial report, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 28)